The last section in the GI pathology chapter
is colorectal carcinoma.
This is a carcinoma that arises
from the colonic or rectal mucosa.
The peak incidence is about 60 to 70 years of age.
Recall that colorectal carcinoma
is the third most common site of cancer
when you exclude skin,
and it's also the third most common cause
of cancer-related death.
Now, when you think about the molecular mechanism
by which colorectal carcinoma can arise,
there's really two major molecular pathways.
The first molecular pathway is the adenoma carcinoma sequence,
and we discussed the adenoma carcinoma sequence
in extensive detail in the prior lecture.
However, this is the most common pathway
by which colorectal carcinoma would arise,
and it probably represents about 80%
of colorectal carcinoma.
There's a second important molecular pathway,
and that's the microsatellite instability pathway.
Now, what is this pathway?
Well, let's begin by reminding ourselves
about what microsatellites are.
So, microsatellites are repeating sequences
of non-coding DNA.
They're present in our DNA,
and every time we have cell division
and we copy our DNA,
we also copy the microsatellites.
Normally, when we have cell division,
we will copy the microsatellites
exactly the way they are,
and we call that microsatellite stability.
Now, let's pretend, for example,
or let's assume, for example,
that the patient has some defect
in DNA copy mechanisms.
For example, they have a problem
with their DNA mismatch repair enzymes.
Well, in that particular case,
they may not be able to maintain
the stability of their microsatellites
as they copy the DNA over and over again,
and this would introduce
something called instability,
and that's exactly what we mean
when we say that there is a molecular pathway
called microsatellite instability,
i.e., there are problems
with the DNA copy mechanism
so that the microsatellites become unstable.
Now, of course,
if the microsatellites are unstable,
that's a sign that other genes
would also be unstable,
and therefore, mutations in other genes
could potentially lead
to the development
of a colorectal carcinoma.
The prototypic example
of this particular pathway,
of the microsatellite instability pathway,
is called hereditary
nonpolyposis colorectal carcinoma.
Now, hereditary implies
that it's an inherited problem,
and in fact,
it's an inherited mutation
in the DNA mismatch repair enzymes.
Nonpolyposis indicates
that the tumors usually arise de novo,
meaning you don't get an adenoma
that becomes a carcinoma.
You simply get the carcinoma over time.
And then colorectal carcinoma
indicates what type of tumor
these patients get.
They have an increased risk
for colorectal carcinoma.
However,
because there is an inherited defect
in all of the cells,
there is also an increased risk
in a couple other organs.
In particular,
it's worth knowing
that patients with HNPCC
also have an increased risk
of ovarian and endometrial carcinoma.
And that's particularly
high yield to know
that these patients get
basically three types of tumors,
colorectal, ovarian,
and endometrial carcinomas.
So these are the two pathways
by which colon cancer can arise.
And it's probably important to note
that there's sort of
a couple other patients
that classically also get
colorectal carcinoma
that you also want to think about
when you think about pathways, per se.
One would be to remember
that patients with ulcerative colitis
have an increased risk
for colorectal carcinoma,
and that sort of occurs independently.
It's really the chronic inflammation
that leads to the increased risk
for development of cancer.
And then remember that patients
with Putz-Jager syndrome
also have an increased risk
for colorectal carcinoma.
So there are a few others.
However, of course,
the two major pathways
and what represents
the vast majority
of colorectal carcinoma
is the adenoma carcinoma sequence.
That's one example.
And then the other one
would be the microsatellite
instability pathway,
the prototypic example
of which is HNPCC.
Now, screening for colorectal carcinoma,
just generally speaking,
it occurs via two mechanisms.
Number one is colonoscopy.
And I note here
that your book actually says endoscopy,
and I'm purposely highlighting this for you.
It should not say endoscopy.
It should say colonoscopy.
So please do correct that.
So again, the first mechanism
for screening for colorectal carcinoma
occurs via colonoscopy.
And the second is
fecal occult blood testing.
Usually we begin screening
at the age of 50.
The idea for colonoscopy
is to remove adenominus polyps.
Again, you want to remove all polyps
because you can't tell
which ones are adenominus
when you do the colonoscopy.
However, the goal was
to remove the adenominus ones.
And so we remove the adenominus polyps
before they can become cancer.
And at the same time,
we also try to detect cancer
before it presents any clinical symptoms.
So that's the goal of colonoscopy.
Fecal occult blood testing
does the same thing.
It also has the ability
to detect bleeding.
And bleeding could be seen with polyps
and it could be seen with cancer.
So it's a mechanism
by which we are, again,
trying to detect both polyps
and, again, also trying to detect cancer
before clinical symptoms arise.
Now, it's important to also note
that cancer can develop
anywhere along the entire length of the colon.
Left-sided carcinoma
usually grows as a napkin ring lesion.
And the idea here is
that if you've got a left-sided cancer,
it tends to grow circumferentially
around the entire lumen
and it squeezes down on the lumen
as if a ring would squeeze on a napkin.
And so they call that a napkin ring lesion.
Now, the classical clinical features
of such a lesion would be
that there would be decreased stool caliber.
Now, imagine if the stool
is coming through here,
as it gets squeezed to the napkin ring,
it will create pencil-thin stools.
And so the stool caliber would decrease.
There could be left lower quadrant pain.
There could also be blood streaking on the stool.
But I think the number one thing is here,
the decreased stool caliber.
Also important to note
that the adenoma carcinoma sequence
tends to be more on the left side
than it is on the right side.
At the same time,
we can also develop right-sided carcinoma.
And the interesting thing
about right-sided carcinoma
is that it tends to grow as a raised lesion.
So if this is the right side,
it tends to grow as this kind of bump
or raised lesion
on the surface of the colonic mucosa.
Now, again, this isn't a polyp.
It's not arising from an adenomatous polyp.
It just simply grows
as a raised lesion on the surface.
And this would then result
in iron deficiency anemia.
The right-sided colon
has a much larger luminal caliber
than the left side.
And so you don't really get obstructive symptoms.
You get bleeding.
And in particular,
you can see small amounts of bleeding
which would slowly over time
result in an iron deficiency anemia.
And you would also get vague pain.
Now, again, right-sided carcinoma
is more classically associated
with the microsatellite instability pathway.
Again, important to note,
left-sided usually associated
with adenoma carcinoma sequence
and right-sided usually associated
with the microsatellite instability pathway.
Generally speaking,
when patients have colorectal carcinoma,
there is an overall increased risk
for streptococcus bovis endocarditis
so that if you have a patient
and they have endocarditis
and there's streptococcus bovis
growing in the blood,
you better really think twice
about colorectal carcinoma.
And you can guarantee yourself
that this is the type of thing
that examiners love to ask about.
They give you a history of a patient
with endocarditis,
they tell you that it's streptococcus bovis,
and then they ask you
what you need to do next.
And of course you need to examine
the GI tract,
in particular the colon.
Now the staging for colorectal carcinoma,
the T stage is based
on the depth of invasion.
Again, generally speaking,
when you have a hollow tube
and you have a cancer growing
in that hollow tube,
depth of invasion becomes
particularly important
for that T staging.
At the same time,
the end stage is based
on spread to regional lymph nodes,
as it would be
in almost every organ.
And then the M,
or metastasis,
is based on distant spread.
And it's important to note
that the most common site
of distant metastasis
is actually the liver.
So that's where colorectal carcinoma
would go
once it leaves the region.
An important tumor marker
is CEA.
Now, remember,
tumor markers,
generally speaking,
can have three possible benefits.
You can use tumor markers
for screening,
you can use them
to assess treatment response,
and you can also use them
to assess or detect recurrence.
In this particular case,
CEA is not useful for screening.
It is useful for detecting,
sorry,
it is useful
for assessing treatment response.
If the patient has an elevated CEA
at the time of diagnosis,
you would look for the CEA
to decrease after response.
And also,
if the patient had an elevated CEA
at the time of diagnosis
and is then treated
and then comes back
with signs and symptoms
that are worrisome
for recurrence,
you could use it
to detect recurrence.
So these are the two benefits
of CEA.
And with that,
we close off
our GI pathology chapter.